When I was little --
عندما كنت صغيراً
and by the way, I was little once --
بالمناسبة .. قد كنت صغيراً ذات يوم !
my father told me a story
أخبرني والدي قصة
about an 18th century watchmaker.
عن صانع ساعات من القرن الثامن عشر
And what this guy had done:
وما كان يقوم به هذا الشخص
he used to produce these fabulously beautiful watches.
هو صناعة ساعات مميزة من مثل هذه الساعة الرائعة
And one day, one of his customers came into his workshop
وذات يوم واحد من زبائنه قدم الى محله
and asked him to clean the watch that he'd bought.
وطلب منه ان يقوم بتنظيف ساعة كان قد اشتراها منه فيما سبق
And the guy took it apart,
فقام الساعاتي بفك قطع الساعة واخذ يقوم بتنظيفها
and one of the things he pulled out was one of the balance wheels.
وواحدة من تلك القطع كانت عجلات التوازن
And as he did so, his customer noticed
واثناء قيامه بفك القطع لاحظ الزبون
that on the back side of the balance wheel was an engraving,
ان هناك على الجهة الخلفية لعجلة التوازن شيء منقوش
were words.
كانت جملة كتبها الساعاتي
And he said to the guy,
فسأل الرجل
"Why have you put stuff on the back
لماذا وضعت نقوشاً على هذه القطعة
that no one will ever see?"
التي لن يراها أحدٌ على الاطلاق ؟
And the watchmaker turned around and said,
فنظر اليه الساعاتي و قال له
"God can see it."
" الله يراها ! "
Now I'm not in the least bit religious,
حسناً أنا لست متديناً على الاطلاق
neither was my father,
ولا حتى والدي
but at that point, I noticed something happening here.
ولكن في تلك اللحظة .. شعرت بشيء يسري هنا
I felt something
شعرت بشيء ما
in this plexus of blood vessels and nerves,
في هذه الحزمة من الأوعية الدموية و الأعصاب
and there must be some muscles in there as well somewhere, I guess.
وربما في بعض العضلات التي يمكن أن توجد في مكان ما في هذه المنطقة - المعدة - كما أعتقد
But I felt something.
الخلاصة أنني شعرت بشيء ما
And it was a physiological response.
وكان ذلك الشعور استجابة فيزيائية
And from that point on, from my age at the time,
ومن هذه اللحظة .. ومن تلك المرحلة من حياتي
I began to think of things in a different way.
بدأت أفكر بالامور بصورة مختلفة
And as I took on my career as a designer,
وبدخولي في مجال التصميم
I began to ask myself the simple question:
بدأت اسأل نفسي سؤالاً بسيطاً
Do we actually think beauty,
هل الجمال فكرٌ ؟
or do we feel it?
أم شعور ؟
Now you probably know the answer to this already.
ربما تعلمون الاجابة على هذا السؤال ..
You probably think, well, I don't know which one you think it is,
ربما تظنون .. أتعلمون لا أعلم حقاً ما تظنون أنه الجواب
but I think it's about feeling beauty.
ولكن اعتقد ان الجمال شيء نشعر به
And so I then moved on into my design career
ومن ثم إنتقلت إلى مهنة التصميم
and began to find some exciting things.
وبدأت أكتشف أشياء مميزة
One of the most early work was done in automotive design --
وقد جرت أعمال عدة في مجال تصميم السيارات
some very exciting work was done there.
لقد رأينا تصميمات مميزة في ذلك المجال
And during a lot of this work,
وعبر مسيرتي بهذا العمل
we found something, or I found something,
وجدنا شيئاً .. وجدت شيئاً
that really fascinated me, and maybe you can remember it.
أبهرني حقاً .. و ربما يمكنكم تذكره
Do you remember when lights used to just go on and off,
هل تذكرون كيف كانت أضواء السيارة الداخلية تعمل و تنطفىء
click click, when you closed the door in a car?
إنارة / إطفاء , عندما نغلق الباب أو نفتحه
And then somebody, I think it was BMW,
ومن ثم قام أحدهم , أعتقد أنها شركة بي إم دبليو
introduced a light that went out slowly.
بتقديم ضوء يخفت بصورة تدريجية
Remember that?
أتذكرون ذلك ؟
I remember it clearly.
أنا أتذكر ذلك بوضوح
Do you remember the first time you were in a car and it did that?
هل تذكرون أول مرة جلستم في سيارة تخفت إنارتها بتدرج
I remember sitting there thinking, this is fantastic.
أتذكر أني جلست في السيارة أفكر , أن هذا أمرٌ رائع
In fact, I've never found anybody
في الحقيقة .. لم أصادف شخصاً
that doesn't like the light that goes out slowly.
لم تعجبه الاضاءة التي تخفت بتدرج
I thought, well what the hell's that about?
ففكرت , ما السر العظيم في هذا ؟
So I started to ask myself questions about it.
وبدأت أطرح الأسئلة في هذا الخصوص
And the first was, I'd ask other people: "Do you like it?" "Yes."
وكان أول سؤال أطرحه على الناس : " هل أحببت هذه الفكرة ؟ " - " نعم "
"Why?" And they'd say, "Oh, it feels so natural,"
" لماذا ؟ " و تكون الاجابة عادة " إنها تبدو طبيعية "
or, "It's nice."
أو " أمرٌ جميل "
I thought, well that's not good enough.
ولكن لم تكن إجابة مقنعة
Can we cut down a little bit further,
هل يمكنكم أن تغوصوا في الامر أكثر ..
because, as a designer, I need the vocabulary, I need the keyboard,
لانني مصمم .. فأنا احتاج الوضوح في التعابير .. أحتاج كلمات
of how this actually works.
عن كيفية عمل هذه الامور و تأثيرها علينا
And so I did some experiments.
وقد قمت ببعض التجارب
And I suddenly realized
وأدركت فجأة
that there was something that did exactly that --
ان هناك شيء في الحياة يقوم بذات الامر
light to dark in six seconds --
اقصد الانتقال من الاضاءة الى العتمة بستة ثواني
exactly that.
تماماً
Do you know what it is? Anyone?
هل تعلمون ما هو ؟ هل يعلم أحدكم ؟
You see, using this bit, the thinky bit,
كما ترون .. الومضات العصبية .. ومضة خاصية التفكير
the slow bit of the brain -- using that.
انها ومضة بطيئة في الدماغ تشابه هذا الامر
And this isn't a think, it's a feel.
في الحقيقة لا اعتقد انها خاصية التفكير .. انها الشعور
And would you do me a favor?
وهل أسديتم لي خدمة ؟
For the next 14 minutes or whatever it is,
في ال14 دقيقة القادمة .. او ما بقي من المحادثة
will you feel stuff?
إشعروا بالأشياء
I don't need you to think so much as I want you to feel it.
لا اريدكم أن تفكروا بالقدر الذي أريدكم أن تشعروا بالاشياء فيه
I felt a sense of relaxation
لقد شعرت بالارتياح
tempered with anticipation.
وبقليل من الترقب
And that thing that I found
وأشعر بذلك
was the cinema or the theater.
عندما اكون في السينما او المسرح
It's actually just happened here --
في الحقيقة لقد حدث ذات الامر هنا
light to dark in six seconds.
- الانتقال من الضوء للعتمة خلال 6 ثوان -
And when that happens, are you sitting there going,
أتعلمون متى يحدث ذلك , عندما تكون جالساً في قاعة السينما
"No, the movie's about to start,"
" لا ليس هذه , بل عندما يكون الفلم على وشك البدء "
or are you going, "That's fantastic. I'm looking forward to it.
ألا تشعرون " هذا رائع .. انا أتشوق لهذا "
I get a sense of anticipation"?
أنا أشعر بالترقب حينها
Now I'm not a neuroscientist.
الآن لست أنا عالم أعصاب
I don't know even if there is something called a conditioned reflex.
انا لا أعلم من الاساس ان كان هناك ما يدعى " الاستجابة الشرطية "
But it might be.
ولكن ربما توجد
Because the people I speak to in the northern hemisphere
لان الاشخاص الذين تحدثت اليهم في قسم الكرة الارضية الشمالي
that used to go in the cinema get this.
عندما كانوا يذهبون الى السينما , كانوا يشعرون بذلك
And some of the people I speak to
وبعض الاشخاص الذين تحدثت معهم
that have never seen a movie or been to the theater
الذين لم يذهبوا الى السينما او المسرح
don't get it in the same way.
لم يشعروا بذات الشعور كما أولئك
Everybody likes it,
ولكن الجميع أحب الفكرة
but some like it more than others.
والبعض أحبها أكثر من الآخر
So this leads me to think of this in a different way.
لهذا هذا يدفعني للتفكير بصورة مختلفة
We're not feeling it. We're thinking beauty is in the limbic system --
نحن لا نشعر بالامر . نحن نفكر به يبدو الجمال في الجهاز الحوفي
if that's not an outmoded idea.
إن لم تكن فكرة عفى عليها الزمن
These are the bits, the pleasure centers,
هناك ومضات في الدماغ تستهدف مناطق المتعة
and maybe what I'm seeing and sensing and feeling
وربما ما نراه , و ما نشعر فيه و نستشعره
is bypassing my thinking.
تتجاوز بعد التفكير و الفكر
The wiring from your sensory apparatus to those bits
ان القنوات التي تصل بين الحواس و تلك المستقبلات ومضات العصبية
is shorter than the bits that have to pass through the thinky bit, the cortex.
هي أقصر من تلك تنقل الافكار الى القشرة الدماغية
They arrive first.
فتصل تلك المتعلقة بالمشاعر أولا
So how do we make that actually work?
إذاً كيف يمكننا أن نستفيد من هذا ؟
And how much of that reactive side of it
و ما هو حجم الجانب التفاعلي منه
is due to what we already know,
الذي ينطوي أسفل ما نعرفه الآن
or what we're going to learn, about something?
أو مالذي يمكننا تعلمه شيء ما بواسطة هذا المفهوم ؟
This is one of the most beautiful things I know.
هذه واحدة من اجمل الامور التي أعرفها
It's a plastic bag.
هذا كيس بلاستيكي
And when I looked at it first, I thought, no, there's no beauty in that.
عندما نظرت اليه للمرة الاولى ظننت .. انه خال من أي جمال
Then I found out,
ومن ثم وجدت
post exposure,
انه بعد تعرض
that this plastic bag if I put it into a filthy puddle
هذا الكيس البلاستيكي لمياه ملوثة
or a stream filled with coliforms
او تيار مائي فيه قلونيات
and all sorts of disgusting stuff,
أو أي نوع من الملوثات
that that filthy water
هذه المياه الملوثة
will migrate through the wall of the bag by osmosis
سوف تسير عبر التناضح العكسي من خلال مسامات الكيس
and end up inside it as pure, potable drinking water.
ومن ثم تصبح المياه التي كانت ملوثة نقية قابلة للشرب
And all of a sudden, this plastic bag
وما إن علمت ذلك حتى ..
was extremely beautiful to me.
فجأة غدا جميلاً جداً
Now I'm going to ask you again
والآن سوف أطلب منكم مرة أخرى
to switch on the emotional bit.
أن تديروا ومضات المشاعر
Would you mind taking the brain out,
هلا تكرمتم وقمت بإطفاء أدمغتكم
and I just want you to feel something.
لاني أريدكم أن تستشعروا شيئاً
Look at that. What are you feeling about it?
أنظروا الى هذا، مالذي تشعرون حيال هذا
Is it beautiful? Is it exciting?
هل هي جميلة ؟ هل هي مثيرة ؟
I'm watching your faces very carefully.
أنا أتابع تفاعل وجوهكم بحرص
There's some rather bored-looking gentlemen
هناك بعض الرجال يبدو على وجوههم الملل
and some slightly engaged-looking ladies
وهناك بعض السيدات المندمجات بالحديث نوعا ماً
who are picking up something off that.
اللاتي بدأن يصلن إلى لب ما أتحدث عنه
Maybe there's an innocence to it.
ربما هناك براءة في هذه الرسمة .
Now I'm going to tell you what it is. Are you ready?
والآن سوف أخبركم الحقيقة . هل أنتم مستعدون ؟
This is the last act on this Earth
هذه الرسمة هي أخر تصرف
of a little girl called Heidi, five years old,
قامت به فتاة تدعى هادي وهي بعمر الخامسة
before she died of cancer to the spine.
قبل أن تتوفاها المنية بسبب سرطان في العمود الفقري
It's the last thing she did,
انها أخر ما قامت به على الأرض
the last physical act.
أخر تصرف فيزيائي
Look at that picture.
الآن انظروا الى الرسمة مرة أخرى
Look at the innocence. Look at the beauty in it.
انظروا الى البراءة .. انظروا الى الجمال
Is it beautiful now?
هل تبدو جميلة الآن ؟
Stop. Stop. How do you feel?
توفقوا . توقفوا . كيف تشعرون حقاً ؟
Where are you feeling this?
أين تشعرون الآن بهذه ؟
I'm feeling it here. I feel it here.
انا اشعر شيء ما هنا .. انا اشعر هنا
And I'm watching your faces,
انا اراقب وجوهكم
because your faces are telling me something.
لان وجوهكم تخبرني شيئاً ما
The lady over there is actually crying, by the way.
بالمناسبة .. السيدة هناك تبكي
But what are you doing?
ولكن ماذا عنكم ؟
I watch what people do.
انا أتابع الأشخاص أمامي
I watch faces.
أنظر إلى وجوههم
I watch reactions.
وردات فعلهم
Because I have to know how people react to things.
لانني لدي فضول لكي أعرف ردات فعل الاشخاص للأمور
And one of the most common faces
واحد أهم ردات الفعل للوجوه
on something faced with beauty,
عندما نصادف شيء جميلاً
something stupefyingly delicious,
مدهشاً , مذهلاً
is what I call the OMG.
هو ما أدعوه وجه " يا إلهي "
And by the way, there's no pleasure in that face.
بالمناسبة . هذا ليس وجه سعيد
It's not a "this is wonderful!"
انه ليس وجه " هذا رائع ! "
The eyebrows are doing this, the eyes are defocused,
فالحواجب متموضعة هكذا , والأعين مشتتة
and the mouth is hanging open.
والفم مفتوح
That's not the expression of joy.
هذا ليس تعبير سعادة
There's something else in that.
هناك شيء آخر في هذا
There's something weird happening.
هناك شيء غريب يحدث
So pleasure seems to be tempered
سعادة محفزة من قبل
by a whole series of different things coming in.
عدة أمور تمت مصادفتها
Poignancy is a word I love as a designer.
إن الانفعال هي كلمة أحبها كمصمم
It means something triggering a big emotional response,
إنها تعني شيء يحفز عدة انفعالات عاطفية
often quite a sad emotional response,
عادة ما تكون انفعالات حزينة
but it's part of what we do.
ولكنها جزء من عملنا
It isn't just about nice.
ان الانفعالات ليست فحسب انفعالات لطيفة
And this is the dilemma, this is the paradox, of beauty.
وهذه معضلة .. و تناقض عن الجمال
Sensorily, we're taking in all sorts of things --
بصورة ما , نحن نأخذ كل شيء بعين الاعتبار
mixtures of things that are good, bad, exciting, frightening --
الخليط من الجيد و السيء و المثير و المخيف
to come up with that sensorial exposure,
لكي نستطيع أن نخرج الاستعراض العاطفي الحسي
that sensation of what's going on.
الذي يعبر عما يحدث
Pathos appears obviously
المآساة تبدو جلية
as part of what you just saw in that little girl's drawing.
فيما رأيتموه في رسمة الفتاة الصغيرة
And also triumph, this sense of transcendence,
والانتصار , و شعور التعالي
this "I never knew that. Ah, this is something new."
المتولد من فكرة " لم أكن أعلم هذا , هذا شيء جديد "
And that's packed in there as well.
وكل هذا مندرج في ذاك تماماً
And as we assemble these tools,
عندما نجمع أدوات مثل هذه
from a design point of view, I get terribly excited about it,
من وجهة نظر مصمم , اغدو متحمساً جداً
because these are things, as we've already said,
لان هذه امور .. كما قلت
they're arriving at the brain, it would seem,
يستقبلها الدماغ على ما يبدو
before cognition, before we can manipulate them --
قبل وعيها و قبل ان نستطيع ان نتلاعب بها
electrochemical party tricks.
بواسطة كيميائية الدماغ الكهربائية
Now what I'm also interested in is:
وما انا مهتم به حقا :
Is it possible to separate
هل من الممكن
intrinsic and extrinsic beauty?
فصل الجمال الخارجي عن الجمال الداخلي ؟
By that, I mean intrinsically beautiful things,
وبهذا , أعني الاشياء ذات الجوهر الجميل
just something that's exquisitely beautiful,
شيء فائق الجمال
that's universally beautiful.
ذلك الجمال العالمي
Very hard to find. Maybe you've got some examples of it.
يصعب الحصول عليه .. ربما يوجد بعض الامثلة عنه
Very hard to find something that, to everybody,
ولكن من الصعب ايجاد ذلك ..اي ان يكون للجميع
is a very beautiful thing,
ذات التقيم الجميل لأمر ما
without a certain amount of information packed in there before.
بدون بعض المعلومات التي تحيط بذلك الشيء
So a lot of it tends to be extrinsic.
الكثير من تلك المناحي تصب في الجمال الخارجي
It's mediated by information before the comprehension.
ان الجمال الخارجي يستسقى من المعلومات لا من المضمون
Or the information's added on at the back,
او من المعلومات التي تضاف لعرض الشيء
like that little girl's drawing that I showed you.
مثل رسمة الفتاة التي عرضتها عليكم
Now when talking about beauty
عندما نتحدث عن الجمال
you can't get away from the fact
لا يمكنك ان تتجاهل حقيقة
that a lot experiments have been done in this way
ان هناك الكثير من الابحاث جرت بهذا الخصوص
with faces and what have you.
بواسطة أوجه الأشخاص
And one of the most tedious ones, I think,
واعتقد ان اكثر الابحاث مللاً و تكرار
was saying that beauty was about symmetry.
هو القول ان الجمال يكمن في التناظر
Well it obviously isn't.
في الحقيقة انه ليس كذلك
This is a more interesting one
وهذه مثيرة للفضول أكثر
where half faces were shown to some people,
حيث تم عرض نصف الوجه فحسب
and then to add them into a list
لبعض الاشخاص وقيل لهم
of most beautiful to least beautiful
انه يتم تصنيفهم بحسب جمال الأوجه
and then exposing a full face.
ومن ثم تم كشف النصف الثاني من الوجه
And they found that it was almost exact coincidence.
وطلب منهم التصنيف مرة أخرى . فخرجوا تقريباً بذات التصنيف
So it wasn't about symmetry.
إذا الامر لا يتعلق بالتناظر
In fact, this lady has a particularly asymmetrical face,
في الحقيقة هذه الفتاة تملك وجها تقريباً غير متناظر
of which both sides are beautiful.
ولكن كلا نصفيها جميلين
But they're both different.
وكلاهما مختلف
And as a designer, I can't help meddling with this,
وكمصمم .. لا استطيع ان اتجاهل هذا
so I pulled it to bits and sort of did stuff like this,
لذا قمت بتحليلها و تصنيفها هكذا ..
and tried to understand what the individual elements were,
وحاولت ان افهم العناصر منفصلة عن بعضها البعض
but feeling it as I go.
وان اشعر بها كل على حدا ..
Now I can feel a sensation of delight and beauty
يمكنني ان اشعر بالسعادة و الجمال
if I look at that eye.
ان نظرت الى العين ..
I'm not getting it off the eyebrow.
ولكن لايمكنني عزلها عن الحاجب
And the earhole isn't doing it to me at all.
والاذن وحدها لا تعني لي شيئاً
So I don't know how much this is helping me,
لذا لم اعد اعرف كيف سيفيدني ذلك
but it's helping to guide me to the places
ولكنه يساعدني في الوصول الى بعض النقاط
where the signals are coming off.
التي تستثير الاشارات في الدماغ
And as I say, I'm not a neuroscientist,
وكما قلت .لست عالم اعصاب
but to understand how I can start to assemble things
ولكن انا استطيع ان افهم كيفية تجميع المعلومات
that will very quickly bypass
والتي تمر بسرعة
this thinking part
عبر قسم التفكير
and get me to the enjoyable precognitive elements.
وتصل بي الى العناصر الممتعة الجميلة
Anais Nin and the Talmud have told us time and time again
"آنيس نين" و زميله "تالمود" لطالما تحدثوا لنا
that we see things not as they are, but as we are.
ان ما نراه ليس سوى انعكاس لنا في العالم الخارجي
So I'm going to shamelessly expose something to you,
لذا سوف اعرض لكم بكل خجل شيء
which is beautiful to me.
اعده جميل جداً بالنسبة لي
And this is the F1 MV Agusta.
هذه إف1 آغوستا إم في
Ahhhh.
آآآآآآه
It is really -- I mean, I can't express to you
انها .. لا استطيع وصف مشاعري
how exquisite this object is.
وكم هذا الشيء يبدو مبهراً بالنسبة لي
But I also know why it's exquisite to me,
ولكني اعرف لماذا هو مبهر بالنسبة لي
because it's a palimpsest of things.
لانها معقدة بما فيه الكفاية
It's masses and masses of layers.
انها تحوي العديد من الطبقات والطبقات
This is just the bit that protrudes into our physical dimension.
هذه تبرز قليلاً بعدنا المادي
It's something much bigger.
انها شيء أكبر
Layer after layer of legend, sport, details that resonate.
من الرياضية و الاسطورة و تناهي التفاصيل والتناغم
I mean, if I just go through some of them now --
اعني .. ان فقط دخلنا في تفاصيل هذه التحفة
I know about laminar flow when it comes to air-piercing objects,
لدي معلومات عن التدفق و الاحتكاك الهوائي عندما يأتي الامر لتلك الآليات السريعة
and that does it consummately well, you can see it can.
وهذا يستهلكني تماما كما ترون
So that's getting me excited.
وهذا يجعلني أتحمس
And I feel that here.
وانا اشعر بذلك الشعور هنا
This bit, the big secret of automotive design --
ان احد اسرار تصاميم المركبات
reflection management.
هو التحكم بالانعكاسات
It's not about the shapes,
فالامر ليس متعلقاً بشكل العربة
it's how the shapes reflect light.
بقدر ما هو بشكل انعكاس الضوء من عليها
Now that thing, light flickers across it as you move,
ان الضوء هنا ينعكس من عليها وميضاً كلما تحركت ..
so it becomes a kinetic object,
وتصبح حيوية وناشطة
even though it's standing still --
وحتى ان كانت واقفة لا تتحرك
managed by how brilliantly that's done on the reflection.
يمكن ادراك مدى روعة انعكاس الضوء من عليها
This little relief on the footplate, by the way, to a rider
وهذا الفراغ البسيط بالقرب من موضع قدم السائق
means there's something going on underneath it --
يعني ان هناك شيء أسفل منه
in this case, a drive chain running at 300 miles and hour probably,
انها السلسلة الحديدية والتي تدور ربما بسرعة 300 ميل في الساعة
taking the power from the engine.
والتي تنقل القدرة من المحرك الى العجلات
I'm getting terribly excited
انا اتحمس بشدة الآن
as my mind and my eyes flick across these things.
حيث ان عيني تجول حول هذه الدراجة الآلية و ترسل الى دماغي ذلك
Titanium lacquer on this.
لاحظوا صبغ التيتانيوم هنا
I can't tell you how wonderful this is.
لا استطيع ان اصف مدى روعة هذه
That's how you stop the nuts coming off at high speed on the wheel.
هكذا تحدون من السرعة على الطرقات السريعة
I'm really getting into this now.
بدأت اندمج في هذا فعلاً
And of course, a racing bike doesn't have a prop stand,
وطبعاً دراجة السباق لا تملك " سندة " إرتكاز .
but this one, because it's a road bike,
ولكن هذه الدراجة ولانها دراجة سباق مخصصة للعامة
it all goes away and it folds into this little gap.
لديها " سندة " إرتكاز تتموضع في هذا الفراغ الصغير
So it disappears.
لكي تختفي لاحقاً اثناء السير
And then I can't tell you how hard it is to do that radiator, which is curved.
انظروا .. لا استطيع أن اخبركم كم هو من الصعب جعل " الراديتور - المبرد " بهذا الانحناء
Why would you do that?
ولكن لماذا قاموا بذلك ؟
Because I know we need to bring the wheel farther into the aerodynamics.
لانهم يريدون ان تنخرط العجلة في الديناميكية الهوائية اكثر
So it's more expensive, but it's wonderful.
وهذا مكلف اكثر . ولكنها رائعة
And to cap it all,
ولكي تتوج كل تلك الميزات
brand royalty --
تظهر علامة الملكية
Agusta, Count Agusta,
آغوستا , كونت آغوستا
from the great histories of this stuff.
من عبق تاريخ هذه الصناعة
The bit that you can't see is the genius that created this.
وما لا ترونه هو العبقرية التي صممت هذا
Massimo Tamburini.
ماسيمو تامبوريني
They call him "The Plumber" in Italy,
وهم يدعونه " السباك " في ايطاليا
as well as "Maestro,"
كما يدعى " المايسترو "
because he actually is engineer
لانه مهندس
and craftsman and sculptor at the same time.
وحرفي و نحات بذات الوقت
There's so little compromise on this, you can't see it.
وهناك مهادنة لن ترونها
But unfortunately, the likes of me and people that are like me
ولكن لسوء الحظ انا والاشخاص مثلي
have to deal with compromise all the time with beauty.
علينا ان نهادن طيلة الوقت
We have to deal with it.
مع هذا الجمال
So I have to work with a supply chain, and I've got to work with the technologies,
لذا يتوجب علي ان اتعامل مع خط الانتاج و مع التكنولوجيا
and I've got to work with everything else all the time,
ومع كل شيء في آن واحد
and so compromises start to fit into it.
مما يعني ان المهادنة تطرح نفسها منذ البداية
And so look at her.
انظروا إليها
I've had to make a bit of a compromise there.
علي أن اساوم قليلاً هنا
I've had to move that part across, but only a millimeter.
علي ان احرك هذا الجزء قليلاً .. فقط ميليمتر واحد
No one's noticed, have they yet?
لن يلاحظ احد ذلك , هل لاحظ احد ذلك ؟
Did you see what I did?
هل رايتم ما قمت به ؟
I moved three things by a millimeter.
لقد حركت ثلاثة اشياء مسافة ميليمتر
Pretty? Yes.
جميل .. أليس كذلك ؟
Beautiful? Maybe lesser.
رائع ؟ ربما اقل من ميليمتر
But then, of course, the consumer says that doesn't really matter.
ولكن المستهلك سيقول انه لا مشكلة في ذلك .. ذلك تغير طفيف
So that's okay, isn't it?
لذا لا مشكلة بذلك .. ألا توافقونني ؟
Another millimeter?
وميليمتر آخر ؟
No one's going to notice those split lines and changes.
لن يلاحظ احد هذه التغيرات البسيطة
It's that easy to lose beauty,
هل من السهل ان نفقد الجمال
because beauty's incredibly difficult to do.
لأنه من الصعوبة بمكان ان نصنعه
And only a few people can do it.
وفقط قليل فحسب من الاشخاص يمكنهم ذلك
And a focus group cannot do it.
بينما مجموعة متحدة فيما بينها لا تستطيع ذلك
And a team rarely can do it.
وفريق متعاون قلما ينجح في ذلك
It takes a central cortex, if you like,
ان الامر يتطلب حيوية المنطقة الدماغية الوسطى
to be able to orchestrate all those elements at the same time.
لكي تستطيع ان تتناغم مع كل تلك العناصر في وقت واحد
This is a beautiful water bottle --
هذه عبوة مياه جميلة
some of you know of it --
ربما يعرفها بعضكم
done by Ross Lovegrove, the designer.
انها من صنع المصمم روس لوفيجروف
This is pretty close to intrinsic beauty. This one,
ان جمالها جوهري نوعا ما
as long as you know what water is like
طالما انك تعلم نوعية المياه التي تحويها
then you can experience this.
والتي تستشعر لذتها
It's lovely because it is an embodiment
انها مميزة لانها تحمل في طياتها
of something refreshing and delicious.
الانتعاش و اللذة
I might like it more than you like it,
ربما أحبها أكثر منكم
because I know how bloody hard it is to do it.
لانني اعلم كم صعب هو الحصول على ذلك التصميم
It's stupefyingly difficult
ان الامر صعب جداً
to make something that refracts light like that,
ان تستطيع ان تصنع انعكاس للضوء هكذا
that comes out of the tool correctly,
والذي ينعكس عن ذلك التصميم بصورة تامة
that goes down the line without falling over.
حيث ينكسر الضوء الى الاسفل دون ان يتبعثر
Underneath this, like the story of the swan,
اسفل هذه .. كقصة البجعة
is a million things very difficult to do.
التي فيها مليون أمر صعب يجب القيام به
So all hail to that.
لننحني لهذا الجمال
It's a fantastic example, a simple object.
انه مثال مميز , منتج واحد
And the one I showed you before was, of course, a massively complex one.
والدراجة التي أريتكم اياها من قبل .. هي مثال معقد جداً
And they're working in beauty
وصانعوها يعملون على الجمال
in slightly different ways because of it.
بصورة مختلفة
You all, I guess, like me,
انتم جميعاً مثلي أعتقد .
enjoy watching a ballet dancer dance.
تستمتعون بمشاهدة راقصي الباليه
And part of the joy of it is, you know the difficulty.
وجزء من هذه المتعة هو معرفتنا لمدى صعوبة الامر
You also may be taking into account the fact that it's incredibly painful.
وربما بعضكم يأخذ بعين الاعتبار ايضاً الآلام الشديدة الناتجة عن ذلك الرقص
Anybody seen a ballet dancer's toes
هل رآى احدكم من قبل أصابع راقصي الباليه
when they come out of the points?
بعد الانتهاء من رقصهم ؟
While she's doing these graceful arabesques and plies and what have you,
فبينما تؤدي الراقصة هذه الحركات المميزة و الانعطافات البهارة
something horrible's going on down here.
هناك ألم يستشري هنا
The comprehension of it
ان معرفة طبيعة هذا الالم
leads us to a greater and heightened sense
تزيد من عظمة و روعة المشهد
of the beauty of what's actually going on.
وجماله الكائن فيه تبعا لمعرفة كنه ولبه
Now I'm using microseconds wrongly here,
الآن انا استخدم الميكرو ثواني بصورة خاطئة هنا
so please ignore me.
من فضلم اهملوا ما اقوم به
But what I have to do now, feeling again,
وما يجب ان اقوم به الآن .. الشعور مرة اخرى
what I've got to do is to be able to supply enough of these enzymes,
ما يجب ان اقوم به هو تحفيز كاف لهذه الانزيمات
of these triggers into something early on in the process,
التي تحفز مستقبلات الجمال والسعادة في بداية العرض
that you pick it up,
والتي يتم التقاطها من قبلكم
not through your thinking, but through your feeling.
لا عن طريق التفكير بل عن طريق الشعور
So we're going to have a little experiment.
وسوف نقوم بتجربة صغيرة
Right, are you ready? I'm going to show you something for a very, very brief moment.
هل أنتم مستعدون ؟ سوف اريكم شيء قصير ومقتضب جداً
Are you ready? Okay.
هل انتم مستعدون ؟ حسناً
Did you think that was a bicycle when I showed it to you at the first flash?
هل تظنون ان ما تم عرضه هو دراجة هوائية ؟
It's not.
انها ليست كذلك ..
Tell me something, did you think it was quick when you first saw it? Yes you did.
اخبروني , هل بدر الى ذهنكم انها دراجة سريعة عندما لمحتموها اول مرة ؟ نعم لقد بدر
Did you think it was modern? Yes you did.
هل ظننتم انها عصرية ؟ نعم ظننتم ذلك
That blip, that information, shot into you before that.
هذه المعلومات و الافكار استشرت في ادمغتكم
And because your brain starter motor began there,
لان محفزات في الدماغ قد بدأت بالعمل
now it's got to deal with it.
والآن علينا التعامل معها
And the great thing is, this motorcycle has been styled this way
والامر الجميل . ان الدراجة النارية قد صممت بهذا الشكل
specifically to engender a sense
لكي تحفز هذه النوعية من الافكار
that it's green technology and it's good for you
انها تقنية بيئية و هي ملائمة لك
and it's light and it's all part of the future.
وهي خفيفة الوزن ومصنوعة من مواد متقدمة جداً
So is that wrong?
هل هذا خطا ؟
Well in this case it isn't,
حسناً في هذه الحالة هو ليس كذلك
because it's a very, very ecologically-sound piece of technology.
لانها تكنولوجيا بيئية نظيفة مفيدة جداً
But you're a slave of that first flash.
ولكننا " مقيدون " بانطباعنا الاولي
We are slaves to the first few fractions of a second --
ونحن مقيدون لتلك الاجزاء الاولى من الثانية
and that's where much of my work
وهنا تماما يقبع جُل عملي تحديداً
has to win or lose,
ويتحدد كوني ربحت او خسرت
on a shelf in a shop.
حتى على رفوف المتاجر
It wins or loses at that point.
الاجزاء الاولى من الثانية هي التي تحدد ربح المنتج او خسارته
You may see 50, 100, 200 things on a shelf
ربما سترى 50 او 100 او 200 منتج على الرف
as you walk down it,
وانت تسير بقربه
but I have to work within that domain,
ولكن علي ان اعمل انا ضمن هذا النطاق
to ensure that it gets you there first.
لكي احرص على ان تلمح المنتج الخاص بي اولاً
And finally, the layer that I love, of knowledge.
وفي النهاية .. طبقة الجمال التي احب .. طبقة المعرفة
Some of you, I'm sure, will be familiar with this.
انا متيقن ان بعضكم مدرك لها
What's incredible about this,
و الجميل حيال هذه الطبقة ..
and the way I love to come back to it,
وما احب ان اعود اليه على الدوام
is this is taking something that you hate or bores you,
هو كيفية تحويل امر تكرهونه او تجدونه مملاً
folding clothes,
كطي الملابس مثلا الى امر ممتع ..
and if you can actually do this --
ان كنتم تستطيعون القيام بذلك ..
who can actually do this? Anybody try to do this?
من يستطيع القيام بذلك ؟ هل جرب احدكم هذه الطريقة ؟
Yeah?
حقاً ؟
It's fantastic, isn't it?
انها رائعة أليس كذلك ؟
Look at that. Do you want to see it again?
انظروا .. هل تريدون ان ترونها مرة اخرى ؟
No time. It says I have two minutes left, so we can't do this.
لا وقت لدي .. بقي لدي اقل من دقيقتين .. لا يمكننا القيام بذلك
But just go to the Web, YouTube,
ولكن يمكنكم ذلك من خلال الانترنت .. من خلال موقع يوتيوب
pull it down, "folding T-shirt."
ابحثوا عنها بواسطة العبارة "folding T-shirt."
That's how underpaid younger-aged people have to fold your T-shirt.
هكذا تطوي العمالة المغمورة الشابة ملابسها
You didn't maybe know it.
ربما لم تعلموا هذا من قبل
But how do you feel about it?
ولكن كيف تشعرون حيال الامر الآن ؟
It feels fantastic when you do it, you look forward to doing it,
انه شعور مميز عندما تعرف عن الامر الذي تنظر اليه
and when you tell somebody else about it -- like you probably have --
وعندما تخبر شخصا ما حيال الامر .. كما فعل البعض ..
you look really smart.
ستبدو ذكياً في نظرهم
The knowledge bubble that sits around the outside,
وستغدو حكيما و تظهر حالة الحكمة عليك
the stuff that costs nothing,
وهي بلا كلفة
because that knowledge is free --
لان المعرفة مجانية
bundle that together and where do we come out?
وبالنظر الى كل ما تم قوله الى أين نصل ؟
Form follows function?
بخصوص الشكل و الغاية ؟
Only sometimes. Only sometimes.
احيانا .. واحيانا فقط
Form is function. Form is function.
الشكل هو ذاته الغاية , الشكل هو ذاته الغاية
It informs, it tells us,
ان الشكل معلومات بحد ذاته ..
it supplies us answers before we've even thought about it.
ان الشكل يمدنا بأجوبة قبل ان نفكر
And so I've stopped using words like "form,"
لذا سوف اتوقف عن استخدم كلمة " شكل "
and I've stopped using words like "function" as a designer.
وكمصمم سوف اتوقف عن استخدام كلمات مثل " غاية "
What I try to pursue now
وما احاول الوصول اليه الان
is the emotional functionality of things.
هو مفهوم الغاية العاطفية للأشياء
Because if I can get that right,
لانه ان استوعبنا ذلك بصورة صحيحة ..
I can make them wonderful, and I can make them repeatedly wonderful.
يمكننا ان نصنع أموراً رائعة .. ويمكننا ان نحافظ على الداوم على تلك الروعة
And you know what those products and services are,
أتعلمون ماهي المنتجات والخدمات التي ستكون رائعة وستستفيدون منها
because you own some of them.
انها ذات التي تملكونها
They're the things that you'd snatch if the house was on fire.
انها الامور التي سوف تهرع لانقاذها ان اشتعل منزلك ذات يوم
Forming the emotional bond
انها الاشياء التي تشكلت رابطة عاطفية
between this thing and you
بينك و بينها
is an electrochemical party trick
انها خدعة كهربائية كيميائية
that happens before you even think about it.
تحدث في دماغك قبل ان تفكر حتى في الامر
Thank you very much.
شكرأً جزيلا لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)